A Guide to the Conan W. Vaughan Papers 1923-92
Digital Library and Archives, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Digital Library and Archives, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Conan W. Vaughan Papers 1923-92
Digital Library and Archives, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ms91-050
1 cubic foot, 3 boxes, 42 folders
The Conan W. Vaughan, Jr., papers were donated in March, April, and June 1992 by Edwin W. Vaughan, Conan Vaughan's brother, of Greensboro, North Carolina. Copies of the Carver/Vaughan correspondence were obtained from the Tuskegee Institute Archives.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Biographical/Historical Information
Conan Wallace Vaughan, Jr., was born on April 23, 1906, in Norfolk, Virginia. After graduating in 1923 from Maury High School in Norfolk he attended Virginia Polytechnic Institute, earning his Bachelor of Science in Mechanical Engineering degree in 1927, and a Master's degree in Mechanical Engineering in 1928. As a member of the local YMCA advisory council during the 1927-28 school year Vaughan was instrumental in inviting George Washington Carver (1861-1943), agricultural chemist and educator of Tuskegee Institute in Alabama, to speak at Virginia Tech in April 1928. The two men corresponded often following Carver's visit, and Vaughan visited Carver at Tuskegee that summer.
Vaughan left Virginia Tech in 1928 to work as District Traffic Manager for the Chesapeake and Potomac Telephone Company in Richmond and Roanoke until 1941. He later worked for the company in Norfolk and Richmond from 1946 until his retirement in 1971. He married Elizabeth Leary Tyler in 1935; they had no children.
Beginning in September 1941 Vaughan served as Unit Commander of the 1128th Engineer Combat Battalion in the European theatre, mostly in Iceland, during World War II. By the end of the war he rose from the rank of Captain to that of Colonel. He received the Bronze Star for meritorious service when his unit was instrumental in the Battle of the Bulge and during the Rhineland invasion preceding V.E. Day.
After the war Vaughan was active in the U.S. Army Reserve and from 1951 to 1959 he served as assistant Commandant and then Commandant of the 2086th Army Reserve Service Unit (Norfolk, Virginia, USAR School). Vaughan received the Army Commendation Medal in 1959. He also served as President of the South Hampton Roads chapter of the Association of the U. S. Army.
Elizabeth Vaughan died in 1988, and Conan W. Vaughan, Jr., died on January 24, 1990. The Vaughans left $2.6 million of their estate to the Virginia-Maryland Regional College of Veterinary Medicine, which is the largest endowment gift in the college's history and one of the largest ever received by Virginia Tech.
Scope and Content Information
The papers consist of photographs, correspondence, awards and certificates, newspaper clippings, files, and other literature almost exclusively from Vaughan's tour of duty (1941-44) in Iceland and Europe during World War II, and his involvement in the U.S. Army Reserve in the late 1940s and 1950s.
Of special interest are copies of correspondence between Vaughan and George Washington Carver, which run from 1928 to 1942. Carver's letters are affectionate and thank Vaughan for his friendship. He often refers to Tuskegee as "God's Little Work Shop."
Arrangement
This collection is arranged according to date.
Contents List
- Maury High School (Norfolk, Virginia) yearbook (separated pages) and class night program 1923 (Box-folder 1-1)
- Military appointments 1926-53 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Certificates and diplomas 1926-77 (Box-folder 1-3)
- Letters and awards from Virginia Polytechnic Institute 1927-32 (Box-folder 1-4)
- Awards 1927-87 (Box-folder 1-5)
- Letters from Vaughan to George Washington Carver at Tuskegee Institute (copies) 1928 (Box-folder 1-6)
- Letters from George Washington Carver to Vaughan (copies) 1928-42 (Box-folder 1-7)
- Articles about the work of George Washington Carver 1928-92 (Box-folder 1-8)
- Vaughan's personnel file from the U.S. Army 1930-50 (Box-folder 1-9)
- Daily Post, -- "Japan and U.S.A. at War" December 8, 1941 (Box-folder 1-10)
- "The American Forces in Iceland," and "Armed Guardians: One Year in Iceland," booklets 1941-42 (Box-folder 1-11)
- Memoranda, notes, etc., from Iceland tour of duty 1941-44 (Box-folder 1-12)
- Humorous and leisure-related literature from Iceland tour of duty 1941-44 (Box-folder 1-13)
- Photographs of sites in Europe 1941-45 (Box-folder 1-14)
- Photographs from Iceland tour of duty 1941-45 (Box-folder 1-15)
- Pieces of a JU-88 German plane shot down in Iceland 1942 (Box-folder 1-16)
- Organization Day programs 1942-43 (Box-folder 1-17)
- Letters to Vaughan 1942-43 (Box-folder 1-18)
- Undated letters to Vaughan 1942-45 (Box-folder 1-19)
- Foreign currency (Taiwanese and French bills) n.d. (Box-folder 1-20)
- Maps of Iceland, Belgium, France, England, and Holland 1943, n.d. (Box-folder 2-1)
- Photographs of U.S. engineering operations in World War II (confidential photographs stamped "passed for publication by field press censor") 1944 (Box-folder 2-2)
- Roster of 1128 Engineers group ca. 1944 (Box-folder 2-3)
- Newspaper clippings and newspapers 1944-45 (Box-folder 2-4)
- Letters to Vaughan 1944-45 (Box-folder 2-5)
- Newspaper clippings about U.S. forces in Iceland during World War II 1944-46 (Box-folder 2-6)
- "Instrument of Surrender" (copy) 1945 (Box-folder 2-7)
- Vaughan's Separation Qualification Record from the U.S. Army 1946 (Box-folder 2-8)
- Newspaper clippings 1946-58 (Box-folder 2-9)
- Newspaper clippings about Malmedy massacre of U.S. soldiers in 1944 (trial in 1949) 1949 (Box-folder 2-10)
- Reinstatement of active military duty 1949 (Box-folder 2-11)
- Letters to Vaughan 1949-60 (Box-folder 2-12)
- Miscellaneous photographs ca. 1950-60 (Box-folder 2-13)
- Army reserve school 1951-59 (Box-folder 2-14)
- Army Commendation Medal presentation 1959 (Box-folder 2-15)
- Application for retired pay benefits 1960(?) (Box-folder 2-16)
- Pencil tray made from Miles Stadium seats 1964 (Box-folder 2-17)
- Award of Appreciation to Vaughan from the Virginia Tech Alumni Association with Century Member bars 1978-83 (Box-folder 2-18)
- Letters from and to Vaughan about his donating letters by George Washington Carver to Tuskegee Institute 1981 (Box-folder 2-19)
- Letters to Vaughan 1983-89 (Box-folder 2-20)
- "The Biography of Conan Wallace Vaughan, Jr." by Edwin W. Vaughan 1990 (Box-folder 2-21)
- "Conan and Elizabeth Vaughan: A Tribute," produced by the Virginia-Maryland Regional College of Veterinary Medicine 1992 (Box-folder 2-22)